

MATTHEW BELL, B.A. Field Supervisor, GIS-GPS Specialist, Draftsperson January 2016



Matthew Bell is a Field Supervisor and GIS-GPS Specialist (including Drafting and Database Management) at International Archaeology, LLC (IA) and International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc. (IARII). He has 10 years of archaeological field and research experience that includes projects in Hawai'i, Rapa Nui (Easter Island), and American Sāmoa. His research has included various types of archaeological studies for federal and state agencies, private clients and academic research. Specializing in GIS database design and maintenance, he also has experience planning surveys, supervision of fieldwork and office work, and report writing. He has experience in the mapping of surface architecture, lava tubes, and topography as well as panoramic and kite photography. He also has experience in surface and subsurface surveys, controlled excavations, and archival background research. Mr. Bell is a specialist in GPS data collection and GPS maintenance and troubleshooting. Mr. Bell's research interests include agricultural practices, utilization of marginal environments, archaeological data management, and the application of remote sensing techniques such as satellite imagery, kite photography, and ground penetrating radar. Mr. Bell has been an author or co-author of over 15 technical research reports and has made numerous GIS, graphical and background research contributions to other reports.

Education

Graduate Certificate, Geographic Information Systems, University of Denver, 2015 B.A., Anthropology, University of Hawai'i-Mānoa, Honolulu, 2005

Professional Positions

Field Supervisor/GIS-GPS Specialist, International Archaeology, LLC, Honolulu, 2014-present Field Supervisor/GIS-GPS Specialist, IARII, Honolulu, 2008-present

Projects Supervisor/Archaeological Technician, 2006-2008, Cultural Surveys Hawai'i, Kailua Computer Graphics Specialist, OfficeMax, Colorado, 2003

Visual Editor and Graphics Designer, Ka Leo O Hawai'i, Honolulu, 2001-2003 (intermittent)

General Archaeological Experience Summary

Field Director/Supervisor, over 10 projects in Hawai'i, 2 in American Sāmoa GIS-GPS Specialist, over 10 projects in Hawai'i and Guam 10 years of active research in the Pacific Region

Recent Pacific Archaeological Experience

GIS-GPS Specialist, MCBH Cultural Landscape Study, O'ahu, 2015-2016

Field Supervisor/GIS-GPS Specialist, KAHO Landmark Nomination Study, Hawai'i Island, 2014

Field Supervisor/GIS-GPS Specialist, SHPD Legacy GIS Pilot Study, O'ahu, 2013

Field Supervisor/GIS-GPS Specialist, HALE Kapahu Living Farm Survey, Maui, 2012-2013

GIS Specialist, Kalaupapa ARPK GIS, Moloka'i, 2012

GIS Specialist, MCB Hawaii MV-22 Monitoring & Testing, O'ahu 2012-2013

GIS Specialist, MCBH Marine Aviation EIS, 2011-2012

GIS Specialist, Kalauapapa Survey, Moloka'i, 2011-2012

Field Sup./GIS-GPS Specialist, Nu'u Inventory Survey, Haleakalā Nat'l Park, Maui, 2011-2015

Field Supervisor, FEMA House Construction Monitoring, American Samoa, 2010

Field Supervisor, ASPA Septic Tank Monitoring, American Sāmoa, 2010

GIS Specialist, various Navy monitoring projects, O'ahu, 2010-2012

GIS Specialist, MCBH ICRMP Update, O'ahu, 2009-2013

Archaeologist/GIS-GPS Specialist, NPS Paumoa Survey, Hawai'i Island, 2009

Field Supervisor/GIS-GPS Specialist, Mōkapu Ground Penetrating Radar Testing, Oʻahu, 2008 Archaeologist/GIS-GPS Specialist, Waimea-Kawaihae Bypass Rd. Testing, Hawaiʻi Island, 2008

Archaeologist/GIS-GPS Specialist, West Loch Relocation Survey & Testing, O'ahu 2008



MATTHEW BELL, B.A. Field Supervisor, GIS-GPS Specialist, Draftsperson January 2016



Ability to Carry Research to Completion

Completion of over 15 technical research reports and 1 academic publication

Selected Technical Reports and Academic Publications

Bell. Matthew J.

Archaeology on Easter Island: Remote Sensing for Low-Impact Archaeological Study of Rapa Nui's (Easter Island) Monumental Stone Architecture. *Hawaii Space Grant Consortium: Undergraduate Fellowship Reports GSGC Report No. 05-13.*

Bell, Matthew J., and J. Stephen Athens

2012 Letter Report, Compilation of GPS Data from ARPK (Archaeology of the Recent Past) Survey into Geodatabase, Kalaupapa National Historical Park, Moloka'i, Hawai'i. Prepared for the National Park Service. International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc., Honolulu.

Bell, Matthew J., Randy Groza, David Shideler, and Hallett H. Hammatt.

Archaeological Inventory Survey of a 224.43-Acre Parcel within Portions of Kohanaiki Ahupua'a and Kaloko Ahupua'a, North Kona Distrct, Hawai'i Island TMK: [3] 7-3-009:017. Prepared for Stanford Carr Development. Cultural Surveys Hawaii, Inc., Kailua.

Bell, Matthew J., Randy Groza, Mindy Simonson, David Shideler, and Hallett H. Hammatt.

Archaeological Inventory Survey of a 360.131-Acre Parcel within Portions of Kohanaiki Ahupua'a and Kaloko Ahupua'a, North Kona Distrct, Hawai'i Island TMK: [3] 7-3-009:025. Prepared for Stanford Carr Development. Cultural Surveys Hawaii, Inc., Kailua.

Bell, Matthew J., and Matt McDermott

Archaeological Inventory Survey Report for the Allure Waikīkī Development, Waikīkī Ahupua'a Honolulu (Kona) District, O'ahu TMK [1] 2-6-13:1, 3, 4, 7, 8, 9, 11, and 12. Prepared for Fifield Companies. Cultural Surveys Hawaii, Inc., Kailua.

Bell, Matthew J., and Alex E. Morrison

2009 Archaeological Monitoring Report in Support of the PMRF KTF Lightning Protection Project. Prepared for Sandia National Laboratories. International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc., Honolulu.

Bell, Matthew J., Timothy M. Rieth, and Christopher W. Filimoehala

2013 State Historic Preservation Division Legacy GIS Pilot Study: Development of Cultural Resources Geospatial Data Derived from Digitized Archaeological Reports. Prepared for State Historic Preservation Division, Kapolei. International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc., Honolulu.

Bell, Matthew J., Mindy Simonson, Kelley Esh, Randy Groza, David Shideler, and Hallett H. Hammatt

Archaeological Inventory Survey of a 194.324-Acre Parcel within Portions of Kohanaiki Ahupua'a and Kaloko Ahupua'a, North Kona Distrct, Hawai'i Island TMK: [3] 7-3-009:026. Prepared for Stanford Carr Development. Cultural Surveys Hawaii, Inc., Kailua.



MATTHEW BELL, B.A. Field Supervisor, GIS-GPS Specialist, Draftsperson January 2016



Esh, Kelley, Matthew J. Bell, Mindy Simonson, David Shideler, and Hallett H. Hammatt

Archaeological Inventory Survey of a 363.106-Acre Parcel within portions of Kohanaiki Ahupua'a and Kaloko Ahupua'a, North Kona Distrct, Hawai'i Island TMK: [3] 7-3-009:028. Prepared for Stanford Carr Development. Cultural Surveys Hawaii, Inc., Kailua.

Morrison, Alex E., Chester P. Walker, and Matthew J. Bell

- 2010 Archaeological Survey and Testing at Former Marine Aircraft Control Squadron (MACS) II Facility, Marine Corps Base Hawaii, Kaneohe Bay, Oʻahu, Hawaiʻi. Prepared for Department of the Navy, Naval Facilities Engineering Command, Pacific. International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc., Honolulu.
- Tomonari-Tuggle, Myra J., Timothy M. Rieth, Matthew Bell, Darby Filimoehala, and Ethan E. Cochrane
 - 2015 Archaeological Inventory and Reconnaissance Surveys of Nu'u, Haleakalā National Park, Maui Island, Hawai'i TMK (2) 1-8-001:002 Volume I: Narrative. Prepared for the National Park Service. International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc., Honolulu.

Large GIS and Graphics Contributions to Technical Reports (selected examples)

Athens, J. Stephen

2012 Archaeological Assessment, Runway Safety Areas 22R and 22L, Honolulu International Airport, Oʻahu, Hawaiʻi. Prepared for Dept. of Transportation - Airports Division, State of Hawaiʻi. International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc., Honolulu.

Department of the Navy

Environmental Impact Statement for the Basing of MV-22 and H-1 Aircraft in Support of III MEF Elements in Hawaii. Department of the Navy and their contractors.

Rieth, Timothy M.

2011 Archaeological Re-location Survey and Subsurface Testing, Naval Magazine West Loch Branch, Pearl Harbor. Prepared for Department of the Navy, Naval Facilities Engineering Command, Pacific. International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc., Honolulu.

Rieth, Timothy M., and M.J. Tomonari-Tuggle

2013 Anything but Hardscrabble: An Archeological Inventory Survey of a Colluvial Slope Agricultural Complex; Kalaupapa Pali Trail Survey, Kalaupapa National Historical Park, Kalaupapa Ahupua'a, Koʻolau District, Moloka'i. Prepared for the National Park Service. International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc., Honolulu.

Tomonari-Tuggle, Myra J.

- 2014 The Making of Mōkapu: A Paradise on the Peninsula. Archival and Ethnohistoric Research of Mōkapu Peninsula. Prepared for Department of the Navy, Naval Facilities Engineering Command, Pacific. International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc., Honolulu.
- 2014 Update to the Integrated Cultural Resources Management Plan (ICRMP), Marine Corps Base Hawaii 2014 2019. Prepared for Department of the Navy, Naval Facilities Engineering Command, Pacific. International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc., Honolulu.
- 2012 Historic Context of the Pearl Harbor Region, Oʻahu, Hawaiʻi: Contact to 1887. Prepared for Wil Chee—Planning, Inc. International Archaeological Research Institute, Inc., Honolulu.